Hey everyone, it's Richard. You're
watching the Plain Bagel. It hasn't been
that long since we last talked about
Bitcoin Treasury Companies uh here on
the channel, but oh boy, it's been a
painful short while for many of these
stocks. Just a few months ago, these
so-called digital asset treasury
companies or DATO for short, were having
the time of their lives. Stocks were
jumping hundreds of percentage points
just on the announcement of their
Bitcoin or other crypto treasuries. and
Strategy, the leader of the pack, run by
Bitcoin and AI image generator
enthusiast Michael Sailor, was taking
advantage of what many would dub the
infinite money glitch, whereby it would
issue shares to buy more Bitcoin and see
its stock price surge as Bitcoin's price
continued to rise. But over just the
past couple of months, the unthinkable
has happened.
Bitcoin's price stopped going up with
the crypto having fallen 30% from its
all-time high reached in October and
cryptocurrencies as a whole experiencing
a broad sell-off with the Treasury
companies who dedicated themselves to
acquiring these assets being hit even
harder with strategy itself having
fallen over 60% since its high in July.
Now, of course, if you zoom out, the
latest correction in Bitcoin's price
isn't really that meaningful on a
relative basis. It really just marks the
reversal of the rally we've seen under
President Trump. But given that many of
these Bitcoin treasuries entered the
space while Bitcoin was approaching its
all-time highs, many of these companies
are now underwater on their investments.
With even Strategy, who's been
accumulating Bitcoin over many years,
having a cost basis that's now not far
off of the current price of Bitcoin. And
it's raised some concerns and questions
over the financial health of these
companies and whether they could find
themselves being forced to liquidate
their holdings and pulling
cryptocurrencies down with them, which
is notable given that these companies
have come to own 5% of all outstanding
Bitcoin and over the past couple of
quarters have been the largest buyer of
the cryptocurrency. Now, naturally, this
troubling news has led to some turmoil
among those who are irresponsibly long
on strategy. And to handle the fallout,
we've seen some investors adopt a
interesting tactic to shunt
responsibility for entering a leveraged
investment on a volatile asset,
blaming Wall Street. You see, over the
weekend, we had some pretty wild claims
circulating online around the company
strategy, ranging from claims that the
US government was contemplating a
multi-billion dollar investment in the
company and was just waiting for the
stock to fall low enough. A tweet that
the CEO sailor himself brought some
attention to after liking to claims that
the sell-off in strategy is actually a
premeditated attack by none other than
America's largest bank JP Morgan with
many enthusiasts encouraging others to
boycott the institution and many online
creators declaring proudly that they
stand with Michael Sailor in [music]
this madeup conflict. Now here it's
worth highlighting that not all the
posts against JP Morgan are specifically
part of this sort of pro- strategy
movement. Uh there are some who have
criticized JP Morgan for banking Jeffrey
Epstein and alternatively for debanking
a number of prominent crypto investors
or institutions. And look, I'm not going
to sit here and claim conversely that I
stand with JP Morgan and whatever this
is. I think there are a lot of valid
criticisms of many of these large
financial institutions. We're definitely
seeing strategy investors trying to tag
onto that movement, encourage investors
to try and prompt a sort of GameStop
meme stock rally 2.0 0 despite a lot of
the claims around JP Morgan sort of
targeting this business not really
showing any evidence and those that do
claim to have again evidence often just
misinterpreting the data we do have. And
so today I wanted to tackle these two
types of topics. On the one hand, what
this decline in Bitcoin's price means
for these treasury companies including
strategy where there's some kind of
disagreement around whether this means
that the company will have to liquidate
if the price falls below their uh
average cost basis or if the company
will be completely fine as the CEO
claims. and then separately at the risk
of being accused of being an industry
plant attacking the JP Morgan situation
and what we actually know about what's
going on there. So, we're covering a lot
of ground. I'll leave chapters in the
description down below if you want to
skip to the different sections, but
let's start off with Bitcoin's price and
what we know so far about its decline.
And frankly,
it's not a lot. So far, a lot of
Bitcoin's price decline has been broadly
attributed to a general flight from
riskier assets. Markets have seemingly
grown worried about uh lofty tech
valuations or the so-called AI bubble
and the uh potential for the Federal
Reserve to hold off on further rate cuts
given that it see signs of a weakening
economy but still wants to keep
inflation under control. And over the
last little while, we've seen signs that
the restrictive monetary policy from the
central bank has started to bite into
markets and started to decrease
liquidity in the system. Uh, for
example, we've seen the repo market,
which is really just a short-term
lending market for financial
institutions, start to experience some
strain with the Federal Reserve's
reverse repo facility, which you can
just think of as a place for financial
institutions to park their excess cash,
having fallen dramatically from $2
trillion to 2 billion. And the standing
repo facility, which you can think of as
a place for financial institutions to
borrow from the Federal Reserve when
cash is harder to access, has started to
see some activity, albeit currently just
a small amount. Now, I've seen a lot of
posts really blow these two charts out
of proportion. But all it really means
is that we are seeing lending conditions
starting to tighten up, which you
generally expect from quantitative
tightening and restrictive interest
rates. And generally when it gets harder
to borrow money, we tend to see money
leave assets like Bitcoin to be used for
other purposes like deleveraging debt.
So while there aren't any clear
catalysts contributing to the sell-off
in the same way that we saw in 2022, we
have seen a general sense of pessimism
take over the markets which has
contributed to the crypto sell-off. And
for digital asset treasury companies who
have gone allin on these crypto assets,
it's been pretty devastating. Prior to
the sell-off, many Bitcoin treasury
companies were trading at premiums to
the value of the Bitcoin they held,
meaning that their market cap to net
asset value or the price per share
divided by the Bitcoin per share was
above one. Strategy in fact saw its
multiple rise as high as three times
during 2024, meaning that investors were
effectively paying $3 to Strategy for $1
of Bitcoin exposure. And this premium
valuation is ultimately what allowed
companies to continue this type of
operation to raise capital by selling
shares uh cycle that into Bitcoin
thereby increasing the price of Bitcoin
and improving their valuation for the
Bitcoin they already hold leading to
again this so-called infinite money
glitch. With this recent decline,
however, that boon has quickly
evaporated. Standard Charter estimates
that with Bitcoin's price under $90,000,
half of Bitcoin Treasury companies will
have lost money on their Bitcoin
purchases. And companies like Strategy
and Metanet, another popular Bitcoin
treasury, have seen their valuations
decrease recently from two times to now
under one times, meaning that these
shares now trade at a discount to their
Bitcoin net asset value. Now, it's worth
noting that strategy on its website does
show its MNAV multiple as still being
above one times, but that's because it's
using its enterprise value rather than
the market cap for their common shares,
meaning they're including the value of
their debt in the numerator, which in
some cases isn't inherently
unreasonable. And as is, the MNAV is a
very limited gauge. But even this figure
has quickly been approaching one, and
it's worth making the distinction that
price per share is currently less than
the value of Bitcoin per share. And this
valuation compression puts some of these
companies in a precarious position. Uh
the only reason the business model of
selling shares to buy Bitcoin worked was
because of this valuation premium. The
fact that investors were kind of turning
a blind eye to math for a second. Now
that the shares are trading at a
discount to net asset value, it doesn't
really make sense to keep issuing
shares. It will actually destroy value
for current shareholders. And in fact,
it actually incentivizes these companies
to now sell their Bitcoin to buy back
their shares since that would be a
better use of shareholder capital. And
we may in fact see shareholders start
pressuring these companies to do that.
The issue, of course, is that that could
naturally trigger a sell-off for the
very crypto assets that these companies
base their value off of and further
exacerbate the issue. As treasury
companies sell, Bitcoin's price could
decrease, thereby further compressing
valuations and forcing further
treasuries to also start selling,
hurting the valuation of whatever
cryptocurrencies these companies have
left over. And in fact, some have
speculated that part of the sell-off
we've seen has been a result of just
this. There's also, of course, the issue
of how many of these treasury companies
actually funded their Bitcoin purchases.
Because in addition to issuing shares,
many firms also took on leverage by
issuing convertible notes. uh something
that works great when the asset is
growing hundreds of percent a year uh
but not so much when the price is
suddenly stagnant or even decreasing. We
may see companies again forced to sell
some of their holdings to meet the
payment obligations that they've
promised. Now for strategy itself,
there's been a lot of debate online
about whether the company would survive
a decline in Bitcoin's price below its
cost basis of $74,000,
the point in which the company would
actually have an unrealized loss on its
Bitcoin holdings. But there is some
truth to the argument that strategy
would survive a price decrease below
this cost basis of $7400.
It's just not evidence that the company
is a safe investment like some are
interpreting it. You see, as of
September end, Strategy had $8.2 billion
in convertible notes and $5.8 billion in
preferred shares. Both of which we'll
refer to as debt here, but are
technically hybrid securities with
features of both debt and equity. Now,
for the last quarter ending September
30th, the company paid 8.6 6 million in
interest and roughly $140 million in
preferred share dividends which if we
crudely annualize gets us an annual
obligation for these instruments of
roughly $600 million a year. Now in
addition to this strategy just this
month also announced a new europriced
preferred share that self will be paying
10%. So if we assume that the company
sells all 7,750,000
shares of this new class, it'll add
another roughly $90 million to our
obligations here. So, in total, we have
a ballpark estimate of $684 million a
year in payments the company has to make
to its so-called creditors. Now, because
Strategy's earnings come almost
exclusively from the price appreciation
of Bitcoin, uh they don't have any cash
flow to pay these amounts. What they do
have, however, is $59 billion worth of
Bitcoin on their balance sheet. So, if
the price doesn't fall further, they
could in fact meet this annual
obligation for quite a long period of
time or alternatively just pay off their
creditors at face value outright. On top
of that, as mentioned in our last video,
Strategy doesn't have standard leverage.
The company's most expensive form of
capital, the preferred shares, currently
offer yields of around 10%. Which is
considered very high. But the reason for
this high yield is that missing a
preferred share dividend to your
investors doesn't constitute a default
like missing an interest payment on debt
would. So if strategy found itself
unable to pay its preferred share
dividends, it could simply skip them
without that constituting a default or
forcing any sort of liquidation on the
company. Meanwhile, many of the
convertible notes which do actually
constitute debt don't actually have an
interest payment that Strategy needs to
make. Finally, strategies obligations to
its creditors here do come with a number
of conventions that again give the
company a lot of leeway during a crypto
sell-off. For example, one of the
preferred share classes can actually pay
its dividend in MSTR shares. So again,
there is some truth to the argument that
strategy is not really on the cusp of
bankruptcy because it has a lot of
rights and privileges with the debt that
it's raised from creditors. But while
that addresses one type of risk, it
doesn't actually make the company a safe
investment. Yes, the company has the
money it needs to pay back its
creditors, but that money will
ultimately be coming from its common
shareholders, the shareholder equity on
its balance sheet. If Strategy starts
selling Bitcoin to meet its obligations,
the stock is likely to crash further. Uh
the company's supposed Bitcoin yield or
the increase in Bitcoin per share would
turn negative. Shareholder equity would
fall as money is transferred from
shareholders to creditors. And any
shares issued in the process while yes
it will help the company meet its
creditor obligations would just further
deteriorate the value of current shares
held by investors given the valuation
discount. Now, alternatively, the
company could say screw over its
preferred shareholders in favor of its
common shareholders to keep its Bitcoin,
but that doesn't put it in a much better
spot, right? Because at that point, the
company is inhibiting its ability to
further raise funds down the road, uh,
effectively killing its Bitcoin
accumulation growth engine, and you'd
likely still see MSTR share price
decrease as, uh, shareholders convert
into common share, and just the news of
it missing payments would still hurt the
price. So yes, technically the company
could survive a further Bitcoin price
decline by liquidating its holdings and
hurting investors, but that's not really
much consolation for investors who are
currently down on their investment. Not
to mention that with Strategy being the
single largest institutional holder of
Bitcoin outside of ETFs, the sale of the
company's Bitcoin would certainly hit
the price of the asset, which could
shift the infinite money glitch into a
sort of death spiral for digital asset
treasury companies. So yes, even with
strategy not being in as precarious of a
situation as other treasury companies
here, there is a reason we've seen this
meaningful decline in the stock's price.
And naturally, it doesn't bode well for
DACA as a whole. But that, my friends,
is where we come to the old ace up the
sleeve, the strategy from strategy
enthusiasts to combat this decline,
play victim to a conspiracy. Again, over
the weekend, we had a number of rumors
about Strategy circulating online with
the one that got the most traction being
that JP Morgan, the US banking giant,
was actually shorting the stock and
trying to crush the cryptocurrency. With
some suggesting that the stock was
actually on the cusp of, get this, a
short squeeze.
Sounds familiar. with some suggesting
that JP Morgan had entered a short
position so large it could put the bank
out of business if strategy rallied just
50% leading many to push others online
to join the fight by buying their
shares. No, those are some pretty tall
claims. Surely there's [music] some
evidence to back up these arguments,
right? [laughter]
Uh no, not even a little bit. The
publicly reported short interest on
strategy is currently around 10% of
their outstanding float, which is
sizable, but not really aligned with
what many are suggesting. And in fact,
this lack of evidence has itself been
used as proof that JP Morgan is surely
hiding a massive short position. But
then why JP Morgan? Why are we seeing
this bank specifically being targeted
here? Well, it seems to revolve around a
recent note on an announcement that
strategy faced the risk of being
delisted from a number of indices. You
see, on October 10th, we had MCI, a
global equity index company, publish an
announcement indicating that it was
reviewing whether digital asset treasury
companies should be included in its
indices. This after it had made a
similar announcement around MetPanet
specifically back in September with MCI
noting that these DACA, which again
raised funds for the purpose of buying a
financial asset, have characteristics
similar to investment funds, which are
currently not eligible for index
inclusion. Now, this was followed by a
note sent out by JP Morgan to its own
investors, warning that strategy in
particular faced the risk of being
dropped from benchmark indices like MCI
USA and NASDAQ 100. Something it argued
would hurt their liquidity and decrease
investor appeal. And this whole issue
isn't really anything new. The company
itself was snubbed by the S&P 500
because of its focus on just buying one
asset. It's not really an operating
company that fits nicely into that sort
of index model. But this JP Morgan note
has been highlighted as the smoking gun,
the irrefutable proof, your honor, that
JP Morgan is secretly shorting strategy
because their note warning about this
risk came over a month after MCI's own
announcement.
I guess the argument is that the
company's looking to dig up dirt and and
bring attention to this old news to to
crush the company. But yeah, [laughter]
now since this initial note, people have
also dug up some other items that they
believe further proves a coordinated
attack here. Uh, for example, last
Wednesday, Empory Digital CEO Ryan Lane
shared that some JP Morgan clients he
was in touch with had allegedly seen
their margin requirements increase
meaningfully on their strategy shares
early in July, meaning they could no
longer borrow as much against the shares
for the purpose of investing. Something
that he framed as a way to reduce demand
for the shares and force selling. And
just this week, some flagged the
announcement by JP Morgan that they had
filed to sell structured notes offering
leveraged exposure to Black Rockck's
Bitcoin ETF with this adding to the
narrative that JP Morgan is trying to
take down strategy and eat their lunch.
But to the first point, on top of it
being hard to verify these claims and
the fact that the stock didn't actually
sell off after the supposed July 7th
shift, it's not really uncommon for
brokers to limit the margin on volatile
or risky positions. In fact, if you go
to TD, another brokerage, you can see
that they too have a restricted loan
value on strategy of 25%. So, bit of a
smaller margin requirement, but still
high at 75%. And you can see that
there's some positions here that don't
allow for any sort of borrowing, which
makes sense because banks don't want to
lend money on stocks that have a high
risk of losing investors money because
it means they might lose the money on
their loan. And last month, Strategy
received a highly speculative credit
rating. So there's definitely this
industry perception that it's a
high-risk position. And to the second
point on the product launch, yes, JP
Morgan might be trying to compete with
strategy on this, but we've had
financial institutions, including JP
Morgan, launching crypto offerings
throughout all of 2025. And it's
interesting because an attack on
strategy won't actually help the bank
with a launch of a competitive product
if it scares investors out of leveraged
Bitcoin investments. Now, there are also
some who have highlighted a recent sale
of 772,000
shares of MSTR by JP Morgan as proof
that their targeting strategy, but even
that's sort of a nothing burger. Outside
of this just being a minuscule amount
relative to JP Morgan and even strategy
size, if you go to the company's 13F
filings, you can see that yes, the
company did in fact sell shares in the
last quarter and does also actually in
fact have put options on the stock,
which is a type of short bet. But on the
net, they actually have a net long
position in the hundreds of millions on
the stock. Now, again, some are arguing
that JP Morgan's hiding a short with uh
swaps and the like, but you can't
really, you know, debunk claims that
something's being hidden. So, that's as
far as I can go. And of course, the idea
that a 50% increase in Strategy stock
price would bankrupt JP Morgan, who's 16
times larger than Strategy and has six
Strategies worth of shareholder equity
alone, is fiction.
>> It's a total fabrication. We made it up.
It's fiction. It never happened.
>> So, it seems pretty clear that most of
these rumors are very much
unsubstantiated uh attempts to just
drive demand for the stock. So, you got
to be careful of any sort of claim you
see on social media or any personality
who blindly cheerleads a given
investment. While some people try to
build this sense of community around a
given stock or position, uh, suggesting
that it's about more than just the money
they're trying to make, we're clearly
seeing people using false narratives
here to try and enrich themselves, which
is funny when you consider that that's
exactly what they're accusing big banks
of doing. And hey, there's certainly
been evidence of that in the past. But
it'll be interesting to see when the CFA
program starts teaching spreading rumors
of a short squeeze and blaming banks as
a strategy for managing positions you've
lost money on. Now, none of this is to
argue that Bitcoin is bound to collapse
or even that strategy is bound to see
itself liquidate. Of course, if we see
the cryptocurrency recover to its
longerterm trend, the company is likely
to follow suit. But I did find the story
fascinating and wanted to take the
opportunity to highlight that for a
business whose sole purpose is to sell
shares to buy Bitcoin, there is downside
risk as we're seeing when those shares
sell off and no longer command that
premium price. Anyway, that's the video.
Thank you guys for joining me today. I
hope you found this video helpful or
entertaining if if nothing else. If you
did, please do make sure to like,
subscribe, all that good stuff. It does
help the channel tremendously. and let
me know your thoughts on Bitcoin
Treasury companies, the current
situation we're seeing around strategy,
and which companies you think uh JP
Morgan is secretly shorting into
oblivion. Any and all thoughts welcome
down below. Uh, thanks again for joining
me and as always, be safe out